Guide to the Charles Telford Erickson Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Charles Telford Erickson Papers
1908-1973
RG 26
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(9 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, and printed material dating from 1908 to 1973, relating to Erickson's personal life and a number of aspects of Albanian history during this period. Letters document the Ericksons' journey to and life in Albania, and interactions with statesmen, presidents, senators and others regarding Albania's political situation. Charles Telford Erickson was born in Galesburg, Illinois in 1867. He served as a Congregational minister before and after his missionary service in Albania, which began in 1908. Erickson served for 12 years under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions and 14 years independently. From 1920 to 1921, he was Special Commissioner for Albania to the U.S. and from 1922 to 1923, he assisted American Legation staff in Albania. Following retirement, Erickson traveled widely, promoting the World Council of Churches and the International Missionary Council, and as a spokesman for Albania.
Erickson, C. Telford (Charles Telford), 1867-1966
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles Telford Erickson.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Telford Erickson, born in 1867 in Galesburg, Illinois, of Swedish parents. He was educated at DePauw University, receiving a B.A. in 1891, an M.A. in 1893, as well as an LL.D. bestowed on him in 1932. In 1895 he was awarded an S.T.B. from Boston University and that same year, married Carrie Louise Earl. They had five children.
After serving in Rangoon, Burma for one year,1897-1898, they were forced to return to the United States because of Mrs. Erickson's ill health. For a few years, he served as pastor of churches in Ohio, and later he spent three years at Yale University where he received a master's degree in 1902. He then served as pastor of a Congregational church in Hartford, Connecticut until he became director of the mission work of the American Board of Foreign Missions at Elbasan, Albania in 1908. Erickson served under the American Board for twelve years and continued independently for fourteen more years. It was during this period that Drury College (1914) gave him a D.D.
During the First World War, Erickson worked as a Red Cross official in Italy and later was chosen an honorary delegate to the Peace Conference in Paris by the Albanian Federation of America and the provisional government of Albania. He acted as a special commissioner for Albania to the United States in 1920-1921 and assisted the American Legation staff in Tirana, Albania in 1922-1923.
Commissioned by the Albanian Government, under Ahmet Zoger, who later became king, to build a national College of Agriculture, he founded two schools; an agricultural school for boys, and a domestic arts school for girls. An American Committee directed the enterprise known as the "Albanian-American Schools of Agriculture". In 1930 the Trustees of the Boys' and Girls' Schools asked the Near East Foundation to assume responsibility for the administration of the overseas work. Due to the invasion and occupation by Italy in 1939, the Near East Foundation, without choice, relinquished their ownership to the Italian government.
Following the death of his first wife (date unknown), Erickson married Alice Lee Welcher in 1936, one year prior to his retirement. In 1937, the Ericksons attended the twenty-fifth anniversary celebration of the Independence of Albania. They stayed at the United States Legation as guests of Minister and Mrs. Grant.
After his retirement, Erickson served as a delegate of the PanAlbanian Federation of America to the United Nations Conference on International Organization which met in San Francisco, California in 1945. He served as inter1m pastor for churches at Portsmouth, New Hampshire, Nantucket Island, Massachusetts, Lake Helen, Florida, and Avalon, California. He and his wife traveled around the world as Erickson spoke to churches and other groups, mostly in Australia and New Zealand, promoting the World Council of Churches, the International Missionary Council, and world Congregationalism. They lived during these latter years at Capri, Corfu, Rhodes, Guernsey, Jersey and Britain, and then finally settled in California. Erickson did not forget Albania during these years but continued to be a spokesman for her welfare. He died in 1966 having lived ninety-nine years.
Bibliography:
Fusonie, Alan E. "The Albanian-American School of Agriculture: Erickson and Hoover. Its Forgotten Benefactors 1920-1939" Chapter IV revised, of Charles Telford Erickson: American Friend of Albania, Ph.D. dissertation, Catholic University of America, 1970. Box 1, Folder 2.
New East Foundation, A Key to the Balkans. New York: 1923, 12 pp. Box 7, Folder 6
Who's Who in America, 26th ea., s.v. "Erickson, Charles Telford"
For further information see:
Minneapolis, Minnesota, University of Minnesota Immigrant Archives. Erickson, Charles Telford "My Retreat from Civilization".
Scope and Contents
The first series, CORRESPONDENCE, although not extensive, does give an indication of Erickson's interests and concerns. The material, dating from 1908 to 1963, was all received or written by Erickson except for a sixteen typewritten page letter by his wife, Alice Lee Welcher Erickson, describing their attendance at the Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Celebration of Albania's Independence in 1937, and a letter written by his son, Paul Telford Erickson.
The letters written from Albania in 1908 and 1909 give a vivid description of the family's journey there, the arrival of their freight, his first attempt at language study and his first impressions of the country. These letters are among the few that are of a personal nature.
Throughout the correspondence there are letters expressing Erickson's concern for Albania. He wrote letters to Franklin D. Roosevelt, John Foster Dulles, and other statesmen, bringing to their attention the plight of Albania, and discussing other current political subjects.
While attending the San Francisco Conference as a delegate for the Pan-Albanian Federation of America, Erickson wrote letters regarding the Conference to various persons including President Truman, Anthony Eden, Senator Vandenberg, and G.M. Panarity of the Pan-Albanian Federation. One issue of concern to Erickson was Albania's rejection for membership in the United Nations.
As indicated in the correspondence of 1940, Erickson tried to find an interim pastorate in Germany, Lebanon, England, China or Hawaii. Due to the Second World War and a variety of other reasons, this attempt to give service failed. However, he and Mrs. Erickson did travel in 1946-1947 and letters regarding their travel arrangements and his speaking engagements are included as well as thank you notes for his services.
The second series, Writings, is divided into three major categories:
Sermons
Manuscripts
Notebook Material
Each of the sermons has a title and usually a Biblical text. Erickson labeled some of the material "Broadcasts", "Easter Sunday", "Communion" or "Installation Service". Sometimes indicated is the location where the sermon was preached. A number of sermons have additional pages attached to them that relate to the sermon topic.
The manuscripts primarily relate to Greek mythology, and the culture and history of Albania, the Balkans, or the Near East. "Little Kingdom What Next" is the only manuscript that is complete. This narrative of 167 pages includes revisions of certain chapters. The remainder of the manuscripts are incomplete; several manuscripts have no title. At the end of this category are folders that contain other writings such as "Articles", "Broadcasts", "Lectures", and "Notes".
The contents of the third category, Notebook Material, are varied. Sermons, sermon material, poetry, prayers, humor, and anecdotes are included. Although most are written by Erickson, there are some printed clippings.
Printed Material is the last series. It includes Albanian language material, church bulletins, pamphlets, newspapers and newspaper clippings regarding Albania dating from 1928 to 1973. One folder contains material written by Erickson.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1909-1968
II. Writings, 1941-1950, n.d.
III. Printed Material, 1928-1973
Congregational churches -- Albania; Missions -- Albania; Missions; Albania -- History; Clergy; Missionaries; Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959; Erickson, C. Telford (Charles Telford), 1867-1966; Stassen, Harold E. (Harold Edward), 1907-2001; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions; Near East Foundation; Pan-Albanian Federation of America VATRA
- Correspondence, 1909-1968; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is filed chronologically from 1909 to 1968 with a description of the contents written on each folder. Letters of prominent individuals are filed separately under their name at the end of the general folder for that year. Most of the letters are originals although there are some copies and extracts. When "Incl." is written on the folder heading, it indicates there are other letters included in the folder besides those that are mentioned.
  - Biographical Material, Incl. Photographs (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Albanian-American School of Agriculture: Erickson and Hoover, its Forgotten Benefactors, 1920-1939." by Alan E. Fusonie ms. (revision of part of his doctoral dissertation): i + 20 pp. + lo pp. (Notes) with cover letter to Dr. Raymond Morris (9/26/71) - 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Re: First arrival in Albania, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Re: Travel in Albania, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Re: Language Study, Arrival of Freight, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Re: Travel Experiences, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - To: Edward Grey re: conditions in Albania, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Incl. To: Woodid Wilson re: appointment of CTE by Albanian government, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - To: Cordell Hull re: present situation in Albania, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - From: Alice L.W. Erickson re: the twenty- fifth Independence Day Celebration in Albania, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Incl: Albanian American Institute, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Incl: "Concerning Interim Pastorates", 1940 Jan (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Re: "Concerning Interim Pastorates", 1940 Feb (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Re: "Concerning Interim Pastorates" Enclosure Re: American Church in Berlin, 1940 Mar (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Re: "Concerning Interim Pastorates", 1940 Apr (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Re: "Concerning Interim Pastorates", 1940 May (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Re: A letter to the editor (enclosed) concerning Christianity in Nazi Germany by H.S. Leiper, 1940 Jun (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Re: "Concerning Interim Pastorates", 1940 Jul, Aug (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Re: "Concerning Interim Pastorates", 1940 Oct (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Re: "Concerning Interim Pastorates", 1940 Nov, Dec (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Incl: Albanian Relief Fund Enclosure: Constitution and By-Law-Preamble of ARF, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Incl: Pan-Albanian Federation of America, Enclosure: "Winston Churchill on Albanian Resistance. House of Commons, Nov. 4, 1943" (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - From: Wendell L. Willkie, 1943 Nov 17, 19 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Re: American Friends of Albania Enclosures: By-Laws, Certificate of Incorporation of AFA, 1943 Nov 24 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Incl. To: Franklin D. Roosevelt, "Editor of the New York Times", 1944 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - To/From Wendell L. Willkie, 1944 Apr (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - To/From: John Foster Dulles, 1944 Sept (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Re: Pan-Albanian Federation of America, 1945 Apr (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Incl. To: Franklin Roosevelt, Anthony Eden Re: Broadcasts to Albania, 1945 May 4-11 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Incl: To/From A.H. Vandenberg, Pan Albanian Federation, "Report on Mission to United Nations Conference", 1945 May 13-26 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Incl: Stanley H. Silverman, Pan-Albanian Federation, Cavendish W. Cannon To: Harry S. Truman, 1945 Jun (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Incl: Concerning trip to Australia and New Zealand Enclosure: ms. - "Operations Crossroads", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Re: Travel in Australia and New Zealand, 1947 Jan (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Re: Travel in Australia and New Zealand, 1947 Feb (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Re: Travel in Australia and New Zealand, 1947 Mar (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Re: Travel in Australia and New Zealand, 1947 Apr (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Incl: Travel in Australia and New Zealand, 1947 May (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Incl: Travel in Australia and New Zealand, 1947 Jun (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Re: Travel in Australia and New Zealand, 1947 Jul (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Incl.To: Herbert Hoover, Thomas E. Dewey Enclosure: On Modernizing the Constitution, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Incl. To: Dean Acheson, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - From: Harold E. Stassen, 1949 Dec 17 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Incl. From: Charles Seymour, Dean Acheson, Harold E. Stassen, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - From: Guy G. Gabrielson, Address (enclosed) given by G.G.G. of the Republican National Committee, 1950 Mar 17 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Incl. Re: Broadcasts to Albania, To: James E. Webb re: clipping (enclosed) in the N.Y. Times, American Federation Movement, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Incl: American Federation Movement Enclosure: Statement - "American Committee for a Free and Independent Albania", 1952 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - To: John Foster Dulles, 1954 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - From: H.A. Cook with (enclosed) Address by L.T. Merchant, 1954 Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Incl: American Friends of the Middle East, Inc., U.S. Department of State, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Incl. Re: Inquiry to write a "history of the Mission in Albania", 1958, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Incl. From: Univ. of Minn., Syracuse Univ., The United Church Board re: material of CTE for Archival Purposes, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - From: Baron Frary von Blomberg with enclosures re: von Bloomberg, 1961 Feb, Mar (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Incl. To: "Secretary of the World Youth Congress, Amsterdam, Holland." From: Paul T. Erickson (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Cards and Postcards, 1936. 1938. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Writings, 1941-1950, n.d.; Series II
  Sermons: Sermons which have dates precede those without dates. Those with dates encompass a period from 1941 to 1950.Manuscripts: Manuscripts with titles are filed first. Following these are manuscripts without titles, and then those with related chapters and pages. Finally filed are those with unrelated chapters and pages. At the end of Manuscripts are "Articles", "Broadcasts", an "Editorial" and "Memorandum", "Lecture Outline", "Lecture", a "Notice" and finally "Notes".Notebook Material: All of the material originally located in binders has been transferred to envelopes. Three small notebooks are the only bound material. Enclosures previously in notebooks appear in this section.
  - Sermons, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sermons, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sermons, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sermons, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sermons, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sermons, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sermons, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sermons (Incl. Broadcasts), 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sermons (Incl. Broadcasts), 1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sermons, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sermons (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sermons (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Sermons (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Sermons (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sermons (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Sermons (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sermons (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sermons (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Sermons (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Sermons (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - S ermons (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Sermons (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Sermons (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Sermons (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Mss. - "Little Kingdom What Next" pp. 1-70 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Mss - "Little Kingdom What Next" pp. 71-167. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Mss. - "Little Kingdom What Next" pp. 1-10, 38-72, 93-114 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Mss. - "When Men and Mountains Meet, The Saga of Albania" pp. 1-35, 64-72, 108-114 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Mss. - Book One "This Strange Brave Fruit" ch. 1-6, 11, 12 pp. 1-32 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Mss. - No Title pp. 7-149 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Mss. - No Title pp. 150-212 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Mss. - No Title pp. 213-246? (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Mss. - No Title ch. 2-15 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Mss. - Related Chapters and Pages ch. 3, 7-14 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Mss. - Related Chapters ch. 10, 14, 18, 20-25 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Mss. - Related Chapters ch. 1, 4-12 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Mss. - Unrelated Chapters and Pages (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Mss. - Unrelated Chapters and Pages (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Mss. - Unrelated Chapters and Pages (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Mss. - Unrelated Chapters (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Mss. - Unrelated Pages (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Mss. - Unrelated Pages (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Articles - "Who are the Albanians?" "Albania for the Albanians" "George Washington and The World's Valley Forge" (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Broadcasts to and re: Albania, 1942, 1947-48 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Editorial - "Russia's Problem" - Memorandum - From Lake Helen, Florida - 1944 Jan 11 "Memorandum of Agreement between The Albanian School of Agriculture, Inc. and Near East Foundation", 1943 Mar 11 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Lecture Outline - "Albania the Child of the Nations" Lecture - "Why The Albanian American Girls School?" Notice - Re: meeting of the Albanian-American School (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Notes re: Albania, Turkey, Greece, the Balkans (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Notes taken by CTE from various sources (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous by CTE and others (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Notebooks (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Notebook Material (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Notebook Material (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Notebook Material (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Notebook Material (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Notebook Material (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Notebook Material (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Notebook Material (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Notebook Material - Enclosures (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Notebook Material - "Source Book For Sermons" (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Autobiographical writing by CTE: "My Retreat From Civilization" (Box 6, Folder 60)
- Printed Material, 1928-1973; Series III
  Printed Material is arranged alphabetically according to category (e.g. Albanian Language Material, Map of Albania, Pamphlets). Newspaper clippings, however, are arranged chronologically.
  Oversized material, consisting of 127 newspapers and one electrostatic copy of a page from The Hartford Courant with enclosure, is in a box at the end of the Papers.
  - Albanian Language Material Incl. Pamphlet re: Tirana (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Church Bulletins, Pamphlet, and Announcement (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Interview: Dr. Nuci Kotta interviewed by radio commentator, Hugh Grant (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Map of Albania (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Material written by CTE Incl. Pamphlet "Until Death Us Do Part," and an Article from The Christian Work, 1921 - "The Youngest Member of the League of Nations", "Life is a Two Way Street" - a sermon (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets - "A Key to the Balkans," "Our Great Task", "Free Albania", "Albanian Relief Fund", "Alamas", "Albanian News Bulletin, 1953, 1957" (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Pamphlets - "A Plan for Peace", "Christian Action on Four Fronts for Peace", "Report of the Pan-European Conference, 1943", Re: American Federation Movement, "Prayer for The San Francisco Conference of the United Nations 1945" (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Pamphlets - "Town Meeting" - 1945 Jun 28 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clip. re: Albania, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clip. re: Albania, 1937, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clip. re: Albania, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clip. re: Albania, 1940-1947 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clip. re: Albania, 1952-1959 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clip. re: Albania, 1960, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Clip. re: Albania, 1962-1967 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Clip. re: Albania, 1971, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper Clip. re: Albania, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Newspapers: Albanian Relief Fund (1 copy), 1948 Sep (Box OV-d6)
  - Balkan Herald (2 copies), 1937 (Box OV-d6)
  - Dielli (The oldest Albanian newspaper in America) (108 copies), 1945 May 19, 1962-1968 (Box OV-d6)
  - Flamuri (2 copies), 1962 (Box OV-d6)
  - Hartford Daily Courant (p. E3 plus copy with Enclosure), 1928 Jan 29 (Box OV-d6)
  - Illyria (1 copy), 1936 (Box OV-d6)
  - Liria Shgiptare (1 copy), 1941 Nov 28 (Box OV-d6)
  - Shqiptari I Lire (10 copies), 1963-1967 (Box OV-d6)